Okay
בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ט"ו, Tes Vav, 15.
We pick up in the middle of י"ד עמוד ב'. Yud Dalet
Amud Bet. It was a little rushed at the end yesterday, sorry
about that. I'm just I guess, what? Yeah exactly. Just to review
in one second what we said. First of all, here where רבי
Rebbi had introduced, was praising רבי חמא בר ביסא Rabbi Chama bar
Bisa to רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose. I
think I initially reversed the names. Anyway, and exactly asking this question
about checking with a cloth that wasn't, hadn't been pre-checked. You know
when they teach כלהs Kallahs they speak about using a pre-checked בדיקה
bedikah cloth. That's where this סוגיא sugya comes from. And it wound
up that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said well my father רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose took the more lenient position and רבי Rebbi took the
more strict. And why was he more interested in רבי Rebbi than
רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? Because רבי Rebbi was, you know, although maybe
the תלמיד, talmid, but he was the head of a ישיבה, yeshiva,
so it speaks about the importance of learning with a group of
people because your ideas get sharper. תוספות Tosfos actually points out that
other גמרות Gemaras where it doesn't sound like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
was רבי's Rebbi's רבי, rebbe, it sounds like a lot that רבי
Rebbi had his student רבי rebbe relationship. And he said well that's
because רבי Rebbi was the head of a ישיבה, yeshiva, so that
changed his status vis-a-vis רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So anyways, this day
there seems like there was a lot of tension going on about
who had what status and who was a bigger תלמיד חכם. talmid
chacham. Anyway, the end of the discussion, right, did end with that
issue about a whole a similar debate about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose about a woman who's who's urinating
and there's blood in the urine. And it was a similar type
of a question which is how much of an evidence do you
need to assume it came from elsewhere. So whereas רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose was more prepared to say where was it
that if there's blood in the urine we just are going to
assume that it's not נדה, niddah, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said it
depends on the circumstances. And this becomes, you know, so here too
it's a question about do you assume that the blood came from
a louse, do you assume it didn't? So this raises, you know,
and I'm just repeating this case to summarize but also because it's
very important questions nowadays when there are medical conditions or possible medical
conditions, you know, and the questions about you know what basis do
you need to assume that the blood is from elsewhere. Anyway it
ended in a whatever it all depends on the circumstances. It ended
in a debate from the range between she's considered a definite נדה,
niddah, even a biblical, to it's a כתם kesem which is Rabbinic,
it's a stain, there is some question where it came from but
in the end of the day we'll say she's טמאה temeiah even
though there is a question but it's still Rabbinic as opposed to
the possibility that she is טהור לגמרי. tahor legamre. Okay now we
continue with the middle of י"ד עמוד ב', Yud Dalet Amud Bet,
נמצא על שלה את אותו יום טמאי. nimtza al shela es oso
yom temei.
So again, if she finds on her בדיקה bedikah cloth immediately after
sex then they can assume they had sex when she was a
נדה, niddah, that they definitely had sex, they're both טמא tamei and
you bring a חטאת. chatas. So the גמרא Gemara says immediately, what's
immediately? So תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan and our rabbis taught this is
the ברייתא beraisa we quoted earlier, right? איזהו שיעור וסת, eizehu shiur
veset, what is the again the time of וסת? veset? Again וסת
veset funny, normally it means the expected period but here somehow it
means immediately. What's the period of immediate checking afterwards that you know
you were she was bleeding at the time? משל לשמש ועד שעומדים
בצד המשקוף, mashal leshamash ve'ed she'omdim betzad hamashkof, a metaphor or whatever
an analogy, not analogy, whatever it is. What's the word? Not metaphor.
Parable! Parable to a to a the you know to the attendant
and the witness that are standing by the doorframe,
בצד המשקוף. betzad hamashkof. כפי שהשמש נכנס עד kefi shehashamash nichnas ed
as soon as the attendant leaves the witness enters in. Okay I
think you all get the comparison here.
הוי וסת שאמרו. havi veset she'amru. That is the וסת veset that
they were talking about, that is what we mean by an immediate
check afterwards. לקינוח אבל לא לבדיקה. lekinuach aval lo lebedikah. That would
count as a wipe, it would not be counted as a בדיקה
bedikah because meaning for the no I don't mean that excuse me,
only if the amount that that after the woman checked she only
did it for the time of a wipe. That's if she spent
the amount of time it takes to do a full בדיקה bedikah
to really do a thorough job, then already that would be then
and then she looked at the cloth, then that already would not
be immediate. Then it already would leave some doubt whether the blood
had been there at the time of sex. So it's like immediately
checking the second afterwards and not even spending too much time on
the check itself. Now נמצא על שלה אחר זמן, nimtza al shela
achar zman, if it's any time after this then they are exempt
from a קרבן, korban, there's still is a doubt, they're both טמא
tamei it's perhaps possibly even ספק דאורייתא, safek d'oraisa, but it's a
ספק safek so they don't bring a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא
Gemara says on this תנא וחייבים באשם תלוי. tana vechayavim be'asham taluy.
A ברייתא beraisa says yes they're exempt from a חטאת chatas because
there's a doubt now whether they had sex during נדה, niddah, but
it's still a אשם תלוי, asham taluy, a sin an אשם asham
that you bring because of a potential sin, there's still a good
chance that they did the sin. ותנא דידן מאי טעמא, ve'tana didan
mai ta'ama, and our תנא tana who did not mention this where
it sounds like you could read our משנה mishnah either way but
it sounds like in our משנה mishnah there's no קרבן, korban, he
says
it's exempt from
a קרבן, korban, it could be חטאת, chatas, but anyway what we're
reading it you're totally exempt, why are you totally exempt? What about
the אשם תלוי? asham taluy? בעינן חתיכה משתי חתיכות, ba'inan chaticha mishte
chatichos,
because if you remember when we were in כריתות, Kereisos, it's not
enough that you have a doubt that you sinned, you might need
an objective basis. Now here you do have an objective basis, there's
blood a few seconds later... But the objective basis might be very
specifically the idea that there's איסור Issur and היתר Heter in front
of you, you did one, you don't know which one you did.
So here at the moment of the sin, you didn't know that
there was a נדה, Niddah, the man didn't know that the נדה
Niddah was in front of him, the woman didn't know that she
was a נדה, Niddah, right. At the moment of the sin there
was not clear איסור. Issur. Afterwards there's clear איסור, Issur, but at
the moment of the sin there was not and therefore there would
not be a basis for an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. Okay. Now,
איזו אחר זמן, Eizu achar zman, now the משנה Mishnah says later
than that, then it is a
so the משנה Mishnah says if it's immediate then it's a חטאת,
Chatas, if it's afterwards then it's a טמא מספק, tamei misafek, both
of them, and then it says and what is considered later? Later
is the time it takes to get off the bed and check.
And then it says and after that then you'll it's only the
24 hours and it's only the rabbinic and the husband is tamei
for touching a נדה Niddah as we'll see but not tamei for
the status of a נדה Niddah himself of having sex with a
נדה Niddah because this is a rabbinic category, the 24 hours. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, ורמינהו, U'reminhu, so the simple sense
of our משנה Mishnah was the time it takes to get off
the bed
and wash, wash the pubic area, that was still the second period,
the three periods: immediate, which is a חטאת, Chatas, after immediate, which
is let's call them immediate, after immediate, and later. Okay, so there's
immediate, which is a חטאת, Chatas, after immediate, which is a serious
ספק, safek, maybe an אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, the husband is equally
tamei and so on, and that's biblical. And then there's later, which
is up to 24 hours, which is all rabbinic. So the משנה
Mishnah seems to say that this after immediate, the second stage, was
up to the time that it took to get off the bed
and wash oneself, up to and including.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to have a little confusion or
questioning about exactly where it draws the lines. Let's take a look.
ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you on that, איזו אחר זמן? Eizu achar
zman? We have a ברייתא Braisa that says what's afterwards? פירש רבי
אליעזר ברבי צדוק כדי שתשלח יד תחת הכר או תחת הכסת ותטול
עד ותבדוק בו. Peresh Rabbi Eliezer b'rabbi Tzadok k'dei shetishlach yad tachas
hakar o tachas hakeses vetitol eyd vetivdok bo. The time it takes
to stick your hand underneath the pillow to grab a cloth and
to check. Okay, so that is already in the second period, in
the after immediate, because the immediate is you're checking a second after.
Here, you gotta grab the cloth and then check. So that actually
is already in the after immediate. So which is it? Our משנה
Mishnah said the after immediate was getting off the bed. This says
the after immediate is grabbing a בדיקה bedika cloth and doing a
check. So which is it? So אמר רב חסדא מאי אחר אחר
אחר. Amar Rav Chisda mai achar achar achar. So when our משנה
Mishnah says later, it means it means later than the later. When
our משנה Mishnah says the the after time, it meant the after
the after. Our משנה Mishnah was talking about the third period, not
the second period. So the second period begins at the time it
takes to grab a to grab a בדיקה bedika cloth meaning, the
immediate is you have the בדיקה bedika cloth in your hand. The
second time is, no, you had to grab the בדיקה bedika cloth.
And the third time begins once it's at the time it took
it would take somebody to get off the bed. So what our
משנה Mishnah says getting off the bed, that's actually the beginning of
the third period, not the beginning of the second period.
It's the only way this immediate would be in a case she's
actually with a בדיקה bedika cloth in her hand.
Right. Right. Before they separate she says wait, let me grab a
בדיקה bedika cloth and then as soon as they separate she does
her check. That's the משל mashal they gave, it's pretty, it's like
it'll never happen. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
The גמרא Gemara says והתניא עלה נמצא על שלו לאחר זמן טמא
מספק ופטור מן הקרבן איזו אחר זמן כדי שתרד מן המטה ותדיח
פניה? Ve'hatanya ala nimsa al shelo l'achar zman tamei misafek upatur min
hakorban eizu achar zman k'dei sheteired min hamita vetadiach paneha? What do
you mean? The משנה Mishnah says that when are you in the
second period about a ספק, safek, you know, and maybe even an
אשם תלוי? Asham Taluy? It says it says what is that time?
The time it takes to get off the bed. So it clearly
says that that time of getting off the bed is the second
period, not the third period. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי
קאמר. hachi ka'amar. איזו אחר זמן כדי שתשלח יד תחת הכר או
תחת הכסת ותטול עד ותבדוק בו וכדי שתרד מן המטה ותדיח פניה.
eizu achar zman k'dei shetishlach yad tachas hakar o tachas hakeses vetitol
eyd vetivdok bo u'k'dei sheteired min hamita vetadiach paneha. No, it's like
it's missing some words. It's like here's what the משנה Mishnah should
say. What is the immediate afterwards? What's the second period? כדי שתשלח
יד תחת הכר או תחת הכסת ותטול עד ותבדוק בו, k'dei shetishlach
yad tachas hakar o tachas hakeses vetitol eyd vetivdok bo, that she
sticks her hand under the pillow to get a cloth. That's the
second period. וכדי. u'k'dei.
Now, when it says getting off the bed, שתרד מן המטה ותדיח
פניה, sheteired min hamita vetadiach paneha, when
once you're already at the time that it took you to get
off the bed, that already is in the third period. That's מחלוקת
רבי עקיבא וחכמים. machlokes Rabbi Akiva v'chachamim. That's the pure rabbinic. That's
24 hours. That's where the חכמים chachamim say that the husband is
not tamei as you know the full level, he's only a secondary
level. That's the third period. So the גמרא Gemara says what do
you mean? ואחר כך תניא, ve'acharkach tanya, the משנה Mishnah says after
this time is when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים chachamim
debate. But the time of getting off the bed, it sounds very
clear in the משנה Mishnah is the second period and it says
later than that time, that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and the חכמים. chachamim. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר.
hachi ka'amar.
When it says אחר כך, acharkach, it doesn't mean after the time
we just said. It means זהו אחר כך שנחלקו בו רבי עקיבא
וחכמים. zehu acharkach shenechelku bo Rabbi Akiva v'chachamim. This period of getting
off the bed, this is the afterwards that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and the so it says when you get off the bed, afterwards
is the debate.
So it’s a little confusing, but to simplify it, it’s really, I
mean, it’s a hard read of the משנה Mishnah if you go
back and look at the משנה Mishnah and see what a stretch
it is. But conceptually it’s not hard. We have three periods. You’re,
you know, checking the second afterwards,
grabbing the בדיקה Bedikah cloth is another period, and getting off the
bed is a third period. So our משנה, Mishnah, it sounded like
both those two things I said were being described as the second
period. The גמרא Gemara resolves it by saying no. The ברייתא Baraita
that’s saying grabbing the בדיקה Bedikah cloth, that’s the second, the משנה
Mishnah that talks about getting off the bed, that is the third
period. It sounds like the משנה Mishnah is the second, but it’s
really the third. Again, what’s the difference between the second and the
third? The second period is could be an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui,
is a real biblical ספק. safek. The husband is as טמא tamei
as the wife. The third period is clearly rabbinic. The husband is
טמא tamei for touching his wife who is a נדה, niddah, but
not as the נדה niddah himself because it is afterwards. Well, that’s
מחלוקת רבי עקיבא וחכמים. machlokes Rebbe Akiva veChachamim.
So we’ve divided it now into three times and reconciled all the
sources. Now the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we? רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב
אשי Rav Ashi says another approach. לא, אידי ואידי חד הוא, no,
idi ve’idi r’hu,
grabbing the cloth under the pillow and getting off the bed are
two ways of describing the same time. You know, sometimes this would
be so much easier if they had seconds and minutes, but okay.
Are at the same time. But how are they the same time?
It clearly takes more time to get off the bed. No, here’s
how they’re the same time. הא בידה כדי שתצא מן המטה ותדיח
פניה. ha beyadah kedei sheteitzei min hamitah vetadiach paneha. If she’s holding
on the cloth then it’s then we’re talking about getting off the
bed, and presumably תדיח tadiach here doesn’t mean rinsing with water or
whatever, it means wiping yourself, maybe it even means checking yourself. So
holding the cloth and getting off the bed is equal to אין
בידה כדי שתאושיט ידה לתחת הכר או לתחת הכסת. ein beyadah kedei
shetoshit yadah letachat hakar o letachat hakeses. Not holding the cloth and
have to grab the cloth. Certainly it takes time to get off
the bed, but it also takes time to grab the cloth. So
if we had one thing describing grabbing the cloth under the pillow
and doing a check, and another thing describing getting off the bed,
so the grabbing of the cloth takes time to grab the cloth,
the getting off the bed is if you don’t have to grab
the cloth you’re already holding onto a cloth.
It doesn’t say it takes so much time to grab a cloth
under the pillow that you’re on, anyway.
Doesn’t say it takes so much time to get off the bed,
right? So he says, he tries to claim they’re the same time,
they’re both describing period two, not period three. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara is going to quote another ברייתא Baraita about this.
מיתיבי, meisivei, I’ll ask you on this. Excuse me, we have a
ברייתא. Baraita. איזהו אחר זמן? eizehu achar zman? What is afterwards? So
זהו דבר, zehu davar, again we don’t know, does after mean second
period or third period? We’ll take a look. דבר זה שאל רבי
אליעזר ברבי צדוק לפני חכמים באושא. davar zeh she’al Rebbe Eliezer beRebbe
Tzadok lifnei Chachamim be’Usha. So רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק Rebbe Eliezer beRebbe
Tzadok
asked the council of sages in אושא Usha this question. ואמר להם,
ve’amar lahem, and he said to them what he wanted to know,
you know, what is this? Is there a second period where it’s
a real ספק, safek, it’s an אשם תלוי? Asham Talui? There’s a
third period where it’s only rabbinic? So he said, look, maybe this
is a moot question for you. Why would it be a moot
question? Let’s look at the top of טו עמוד א. tes vav
amud aleph. שמא כרבי עקיבא אתם אומרים? shema keRebbe Akiva atem omrim?
Maybe you פוסקן posken like רבי עקיבא? Rebbe Akiva? רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva says even in the third period, the husband is as טמא
tamei as the wife. שמא תטמא בעלה, shema tetamei ba’alah, that even
in the third period, even within the twenty-four hours, the woman who
has sex with her husband, the husband is as טמא tamei as
the wife. And therefore it’s a pretty much a moot question. What’s
the נפקא מינא nafka mina of the second and third? The primary
נפקא מינא nafka mina is whether the husband is as טמא כבעלה.
tamei keba’alah. There’s also a potential נפקא מינא nafka mina about an
אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, but א, alef, you don’t have a בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and ב, beis, we said our משנה Mishnah was
assuming no אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. So the really, if you held
like רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, there’s very little difference between the second
and the third period.
Most things are דאורייתא. de’oraisa.
Alright, but practically there’s very little difference. So maybe you don’t bother
making the distinction between those times. אמרו לו לא שמענו. amru lo
lo shamanu. No, we haven’t heard of רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, meaning
we don’t פוסקן posken like רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. So if you
don’t פוסקן posken like רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, you have to distinguish
between the second period and the third period. אמר להם, amar lahem,
so again it’s interesting, they apparently didn’t have an answer and like
that sort of seems to be edited out. He said what is
this third period? They said we don’t know. So he said why
don’t you know? That’s not in there, but what you have to
speculate that’s what’s happening. Turns out why don’t you know? Maybe you
פוסקן posken like רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and there’s no difference between
the second and the third period practically. So they said no, we
don’t פוסקן posken like רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. He says okay, so
you don’t know what the difference is? I’ll tell you what the
difference is. Here’s what the difference is, the time between the second
period and the third period.
To just give your answer.
Well maybe he wanted to hear their answer but they didn’t have,
so he wanted to say alright so at least I’ll tell you
what you know, my prediction about this.
Why אושא? Usha?
אושא Usha was where the בית דין Beis Din sort of moved
after יבנה. Yavneh. There were a lot of תקנות, takkanot, especially around
כתובה ketuvah issues. There were a lot of תקנות, takkanot, so we’ll
see that a lot when we do כתובות ketuvos about.
It seems like a very minor detail they were all in transition
and trying to save Judaism. Exactly. You would imagine they’d be dealing
with weighty.
It’s a good point, but I do think that part of the
endeavor of preserving Judaism was establishing the whole endeavor of תורה שבעל
פה. Torah Shebaal Peh. You know what I mean? It wasn’t just...
But you are right that you are right that we normally associate
יבנה *Yavne* with more the theoretical and getting all of the testimony
and אושא *Usha*, there are a lot of תקנות *takanot* in אושא
*Usha*. We do associate, right, right, right, major practical things we do
associate with more sort of pragmatic issues. So it is a good
point, you know again, maybe they were still עסוקה בטהרות asuka be'taharot
*asuka betaharot* here but it does sound like a relatively minor, it's
a very valid point. Maybe it fleshes out the picture, you know,
even if they're spending most of their time with תקנות *takanot*, they're
still the center of תורה Torah, שבעל פה *Torah she-ba'al peh*, they
still deal with these issues as well. Okay, so he so he
says, alright, so and here's יבנה *Yavne* coming into the picture. אמר
amar להם כך ישבו חכמים Chachamim. ביבנה *Amar lahem kach yashvu chachamim
be-Yavne*. Okay, you don't know, maybe this is why they didn't know,
maybe it's why he had to tell them, they were too bothered
with the practical תקנות *takanot*. So he's trying to get more of
a theoretical discussion going. They don't know, so he says, alright, let
me tell you what we said in יבנה *Yavne*. Here's what the
חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* said in יבנה *Yavne*. לא Lo, שהתה כדי שתרד
מן המיטה ותדיח את פניה *Lo shahata kedei she-tered min ha-mita ve-tadiach
et paneha*, if she had not yet waited the time it takes
to get off the bed and wash herself, תוך זמן הוא זה
*toch zman hu zeh*. That is period number two, up to that
time. וטמאי ספק safek, פטור מן הקרבן *Ve-tamei safeik patur min ha-korban*.
They are טמאי ספק safek, *tamei safeik* biblically and he's טמא tamei
*tamei* equally but there's no קרבן *korban*, at least no חטאת chatat.
*chatat*. וחייבין באשם תלוי *Ve-chayavin be-asham taluy*, this according to this they
bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy, *asham taluy*. This might have been
the ברייתא braita *braita* we referred to earlier. Okay. שהתה כדי שתרד
מן המיטה ותדיח את פניה *Shahata kedei she-tered min ha-mita ve-tadiach et
paneha*, once it takes the time to get off the bed and
wash yourself, זהו לאחר זמן *zehu le-achar zman*. That is already the
third period. לאחר זמן הוא זה *Achar zman hu zeh*. That's already
the third period and then it's only going to be rabbinic and
24 hours. וכן כששהתה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה *Ve-chein keshe-shahata me-eit le-eit
u-mi-pekida li-fekida*. And that goes up till from the time it takes
to get off the bed and wash up till 24 hours, you
know, that's going she's going to be טמאה teme'ah. *tmeia*. Or till
the last time she checked, right? That's the rabbinic period of 24
hours or the last time she checked. It starts at checks that
took place after getting off the bed. בוא עליה מטמא משום מגע
*Bo aleha metamei mishum maga*, the husband is טמא tamei *tamei* in
this period where it's purely rabbinic for touching his wife, because they
were having sex so during that period she's considered to be a
נדה niddah? *niddah*, a נדה niddah. *niddah* rabbinically. No, ומשום מגע *u-mishum
maga*
for touching his wife, which makes him a ראשון rishon? *rishon*, first-degree
derivative. ואינו מטמא משום בועל *Ve-eino metamei mishum boel*. But he does
not have the status according to the Torah if a man and
woman have sex when the woman is a נדה niddah *niddah*, the
husband's טומאה tumah *tumah* is a full seven-day טומאה tumah. *tumah* just
like the נדה niddah. *niddah* and he is an אב av. הטומאה
*av ha-tumah*. So the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
and the חכמים *chachamim* is, that is true when they were definitely
having sex when she was a נדה niddah *niddah*. It's also true
when it was a ספק דאורייתא safek d'Oraita. *safeik de-oraita* when it
was within you know the few seconds, 10 seconds, one minute afterward.
Once you get into the rabbinic period of 24 hours, we're not
going according to the חכמים *chachamim* he will be טמא tamei *tamei*
for touching his wife who is a נדה niddah *niddah* which is
a ראשון rishon. *rishon*, but not as a בועל נדה niddah *boel
niddah* and not as an אב av. *av*. One minute. ורבי עקיבא
אומר *Ve-Rabbi Akiva omer* אף מטמא משום בועל *af metamei mishum boel*.
No, this is the debate in the משנה mishnah *mishna*. He has
a full טומאה tumah, *tumah* during that 24 hours and therefore he
is considered like one who had sex with a נדה niddah *niddah*
and he is an אב av. הטומאה *av ha-tumah*. רבי יהודה בן
דוסא בשם רבי יוחנן בן זכאי אומר *Rabbi Yehuda ben Dosa be-shem
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakai omer*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* the son of
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakai* says, notice by the
way the generations, one generation after רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakai*. Actually this doesn't make sense. This has to have been,
this has to have been edited later because right? No, no, no,
I'm sorry.
Wait, wait, he's the son of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Sorry, רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is already later.
I know but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
is right? רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is later than יבנה *Yavne*. Right?
So he was at יבנה *Yavne* but he wasn't part
of, yeah, I'm not sure, it could be,
yeah but you know, yeah but he actually says it there, maybe
it's like maybe רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was at the very end
of יבנה *Yavne*. Okay, have to check those dates. Anyway, certainly רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* the son of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakai* was you know was right at יבנה *Yavne*, right, רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakai* was the one who established
יבנה *Yavne*. Anyway, אומר בא לה נכנס להיכל ומקטיר קטורת *omer ba
lah nichnas la-heichal u-maktir ktoret*. Says the husband is not not only
is he not a בועל נדה niddah *boel niddah*, he's not even
טמא tamei *tamei* for touching a נדה niddah *niddah*. If he was
a כהן *kohen*, he could go into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash?
*Beit Ha-Mikdash* and bring the incense. Okay, which since so certainly would
appear a period relatively after the חורבן הבית *churban ha-bayit* they're still
thinking about that, pretty extreme. Of course the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to say, how could he not be טמא tamei *tamei* for
touching his wife who is a נדה niddah *niddah*? If you're going
to make her טמאה temeiah, *tmeia* 24 hours back and he touched
her during that period then of course he you have to treat
him as טמא tamei, *tamei*, maybe not as a בועל נדה niddah,
*boel niddah* but at least טמא tamei *tamei*. So anyway, let's just
I'll take questions in a second but let's just see here it
is quite clear
that once it takes the time for her to get off the
bed you're into the third period. Okay, so how does that fit
with the earlier description? So let's just see how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* wraps this up. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this,
בשלמא לרב חסדא *Bishlama le-Rav Chisda*, according to רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*
who said that the period of getting of hand under the pillow
was the second period, getting off the bed was the third period,
that's exactly what this ברייתא braita *braita* says. היינו דמטהרי רבנן *Hainu
de-mitahari rabanan*. That's why the rabbis are more lenient, like they're meaning
not טהור tahor. לגמרי *tahor legamre* but he's not considered a source
of טומאה tumah. *tumah* like a בועל נדה niddah. *boel niddah*, that
they're more lenient because we're talking about the third period. אלא לרב
אשי אמאי מטהרי *Ela le-Rav Ashi amai mitahari*. According to the Rabbis,
why are we lenient in this period of getting off the bed?
According to him, the getting off the bed was the second period
and it should still be full level of טומאה, tumah, אשם תלוי,
asham taluy the whole bit. So he says, וכי תימא דאינה בידה,
vechi teima d'einah biyada,
maybe, here's the answer. When did I say getting off the bed
was the second period? If you weren't off, if you were already
holding on to the cloth. But once it takes the time to
get off the bed and to grab a cloth, that would already
be the third period. So maybe here what we say getting off
the bed is the third period is when she had to get
off the bed and grab the cloth. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, האי בידה והאי אינה בידה מיבעי ליה. hai biyada vehai einah
biyada mibaei lei. Then if it was distinguished, if it was talking
about that, it should have been explicit to say the second period
is when you're not holding the cloth,
the second period is you are holding the cloth, the second period
is you're not, third period is you're not yet holding the cloth,
right? It should have been more explicit.
The משנה mishnah was pretty explicit, how'd you interpret that?
I know, but anyway תוספות Tosafot has another way, anyway קשיא. kashya.
So anyway what we do see here is, and I'll take your
question, is that it's pretty explicit in this that by the time
it takes to get off the bed you're already in the purely
rabbinic period. And the three periods are: checking ממש mamash a second
afterwards, no grabbing a cloth, that's immediate, that's definite חטאת. chatat. The
time it takes to grab a cloth and check, so a few
seconds later, that puts you in a אשם תלוי asham taluy. biblical
ספק, Safeik but not a חטאת. And then once it's the time
it took to get off the bed, that already is a third
period and that's where the debate of רבי עקיבא and the חכמים.
So the approach that says the getting off the bed was the
same as the second period, this ברייתא certainly seems to emphasize that
it is a distinct, that is the beginning of this third period
of the more lenient.
How do you distinguish the first two opinions of this ברייתא that
when you when you're טמא tamei is it if you touched a
נדה?
niddah Yeah,
I think we should be careful to say I just want to
talk about say interrupt you for a second, because I've made I've
done this as well. We talk about sort of the whole objectification
that happens here. I think we should say touch a woman who
is a נדה. niddah Okay, let's go on.
Thank you. Point taken.
While we're saying that, I'm going to make another interesting point, which
is that in the תורה, Torah the word נדה niddah is only
a verb. בטומאת נדתה, betumat niddatah,
in the tumah of her flow. Okay, or maybe whatever. Anyway, it
doesn't describe the person. It's only in the משנה Mishnah. and the
גמרא Gemara that the woman is called a נדה. Niddah Otherwise, it's
just means the word נדה Niddah, in the תורה means a woman
who has is you know, כי תזוב זוב דמה בלא עת נדתה,
ki tazuv zuv damah belo et niddatah, the time of her flow,
not the time of her flow, and so on. So this whole
question about like, you know, labeling and objectifying and so on, it
becomes heightened here. So that's a particular sensitivity which I am sure
I make that mistake as well. Go ahead. Now ask your question.
So a woman who is a נדה Niddah, is a ראשון?
rishon, Is an אב. av. Is an אב. av. As are things
she sits on. As are as is the man who has sex
with her. But but if it's not something she sits on and
it's not the man who has sex with her, then anything she
touches is a ראשון.
rishon, Okay, so this man would be a ראשון, rishon. so wouldn't
he be biblically טמא tamei rather than...
Yes. Yes. Oh, no, but it's but no, no, he touched her
before she checked, before she knew she was a נדה Niddah, in
the last 24 hours. Yeah, so the whole point is here is
they had sex, then she checked. What is his status, what's her
status and his status, when they had based on the fact that
they had sex, but the but she only knew she was a
נדה later. So if the later is a second later, they're definitely
טמא דאורייתא. tamei d'Oraita. Right. If the נדה if the later was
ten seconds later, it's ספק דאורייתא. safek d'Oraita. Okay, and it's an
אשם תלוי. If it was anywhere from ten seconds to 24 hours,
then the fact that they had sex at that time before the
checking is a rabbinic טמא tamei and he is a ראשון, not
an אב. But a ראשון דרבנן. rishon derabanan. Okay, the whole טומאה
prior once they're checking anything prior to that moment of checking that's
more than ten seconds before that moment of checking here's the checking,
I sort of did the visual. Here's the checking. In the space
of one second before, it's דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Ten seconds before, it's ספק
דאורייתא. safek d'Oraita Anything more than ten seconds before that moment of
checking till the last check or till 24 hours is purely דרבנן.
derabanan.
Okay, so if he's ספק דאורייתא safek d'Oraita or if he's דרבנן
derabanan and he touches תרומה, terumah, the תרומה terumah would neither be
burned nor eaten?
No, ספק דאורייתא safek d'Oraita oh, that's true, there are different issues
about what we do with ספק דאורייתא safek de'oraita by תרומה, terumah,
but let's just say as sometimes we actually do do burn תרומה
terumah for a דרבנן, derabanan, but not for this דרבנן derabanan of
24 hours. So let's say definitely for the 24 hours and probably
for the
for simply, I'll say yes, but it's a little more it's a
little more whatever, questionable than that, but the simple answer is yes.
Okay, yeah.
Are they checking before as well? Sex, yes. So it sounds a
little arbitrary that you know, how would they imagine
how do you get up to 24 hours?
No, how do you imagine this distinction between one second and ten
seconds and fifteen seconds if they checked before? But it's a little
more nuanced. It's a little more whatever. Questionable than that, but the
simple answer is yes. Okay. Yeah. I thought they checked before as
well. Sex? Yes. So it sounds a little arbitrary that—how would they
imagine—how you'd get up to twenty-four hours?—no, how they imagine this distinction
between one second and ten seconds and fifteen seconds?
They checked before, wouldn't it be more...
in my mind I'm thinking it would seem that in all of
those time periods it would indicate that she was bleeding when they—no,
no, they checked before and she was טהור. tahor. So she was—so
why twenty-four hours?
So what I'm saying is that between one second checking and ten
seconds checking afterwards, yeah, it would seem that they would both indicate
that she was bleeding while they were having sex, no?
No, maybe it happened from the after the sex till the ten
seconds.
Maybe it started in those ten seconds.
Right, that's exactly the point. But you make a good point, meaning,
and meaning, meaning
if they check—it's possible obviously, since we go back up to—we can
go back up to twenty-four hours, it's possible that they didn't do
what they were supposed to and they didn't do the checking, right?
But in the scenario where they did the checking right before sex,
you know, if they're having sex for a half hour and then
they had—and then checking ten seconds afterwards, just law of averages, it's
more likely, although we would assume that the bleeding probably occurred near
the time of the checking, still, it's pretty like more likely it
happened during the time of the check. That's a good question. So
I hear your point. Meaning even if it was like a minute
out, where now we're going to say it's all rabbinic, but you're
saying, but if you had a minute of not having sex and
a half hour of having sex, right, and then there was the
check here, so it's hard—why are we saying that this half hour
is purely rabbinic? That's a very good question.
Yeah, I don't know.
Yeah, it's a very good point. Okay? But that's basically I think
the way to sort of visualize the idea. Here's the moment of
checking. It's sort of like, you know, increasing bands of, you know,
darker and light—whatever. So the immediate one second back is definite, ten
seconds back is ספק Safeik, דאורייתא and more back from that is...
okay. So anyways let's continue now the גמרא.
Gemara Do you always check immediately, or is it just a recommendation?
So yeah, they don't have a recommendation. I mean, it does say
that they check after. It doesn't say how soon after.
So there is no advantage to wait.
Yeah, basically, yeah. Okay. רבי יהודה בנו של רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
אומר בעל הנכנס להיכל מקטיר קטורת. Rabbi Yehuda beno shel Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai omer ba'al hanichnas la-heichal maktir ketoret. So after this, if
the checking occurred more than ten seconds or whatever—I'm saying ten seconds,
I don't know, a minute—after they had sex, then it's purely rabbinic
and he's not an—and he said he's at least rabbinically like touching
a נידה, niddah, so here why
is
he saying you can go into the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So
the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק ליה דהא נוגע במעת לעת שבנידה. ve-tipok
lei de-ha noge'a be-ma'at le-et she-be-niddah. He had touched his wife, now
she's not a definite נידה niddah in that period, but at least
she's the rabbinic twenty-four hour backward נידה, niddah, so at least he's
טמא דרבנן. tamei de-rabbanan. How would we allow this? He's definitely טמא
דרבנן.
tamei de-rabbanan.
So the גמרא Gemara says
no, הוא דאמר כשמאי. Hu de'amar ke-Shammai. Maybe he holds like שמאי,
Shammai, דאמר כל הנשים דיין שעתן, de'amar kol ha-nashim dayyan she'atan, that
you don't go back twenty-four hours. That according to שמאי Shammai you
have the one second back, the ten seconds back, and then she's
טהורה לגמרי. tehorah legamrei. By שמאי Shammai would certainly agree that the
times we would say were biblical concerns, one second before the check
or up to ten seconds or a minute before the check, that's
definitely a biblical concern, but beyond that שמאי Shammai says you're טהור.
tahor. So maybe he held like שמאי, Shammai, so anytime before—there's no
third period, so he's totally טהור. tahor. So the גמרא Gemara says
ותיפוק ליה דהוי בעל קרי, ve-tipok lei de-havi ba'al keri, but if
he was having sex, he's טמא tamei because he's a בעל קרי
ba'al keri because he had seminal emission, and there he's טמא tamei
because himself he's טמא, tamei how could he go in and be
in the בית המקדש? So the גמרא Gemara says בשלא גמר ביאתו.
be-she-lo gamar bi'ato.
Maybe he did not—now גמר ביאתו gamar bi'ato describes anatomically, what it
really means to say is maybe he wasn't רואה, ro'eh, maybe he
didn't lead to ejaculation, okay, which could be described as finishing, you
know, גומר ביאה, gomer bi'ah, finishing the act of sex. But normally
גמר ביאה gmar bi'ah just to be clear is an anatomical description,
which means the העראה ha'ara'ah which is the beginning of ביאה bi'ah
which is the biblical act of ביאה bi'ah for all prohibitions and
mitzvahs and whatever is as soon as the crown penetrates in the
vagina. גמר ביאה gmar bi'ah is when the shaft is fully, you
know, fully penetrates. But גמר ביאה gmar bi'ah according to the גמרא
Gemara is what is needed to bring about ejaculation. Ejaculation only occurs
with גמר ביאה. gmar bi'ah. I don't think that's medically true. I
think some people that actually have issues with premature ejaculation and so
on obviously can have ejaculation before גמר ביאה. gmar bi'ah. But anyway,
but the גמרא Gemara assumes that that occurs with גמר ביאה. gmar
bi'ah. So what it really means to say is less the anatomical
point and more the point that it could be a case where
he didn't ejaculate. So therefore he's not a בעל קרי ba'al keri
and he holds like שמאי, Shammai, so he could be totally טהור.
Okay. And now finishing up the משנה. Mishna ומודים חכמים לרבי עקיבא
ברואה כתם. U-modim chachamim le-Rabbi Akiva be-ro'eh ketam.
So although כתמים ketamim are pure דרבנן—and de-rabbanan again כתמים ketamim is
not she saw it from checking her body, she saw a stain
on the sheet—so there on the one hand it's more lenient because
there's a possibility it didn't come from her and the first thing
we do is we try to see if we can sort of
attribute it to something external from her. And if we can then
she's טהורה לגמרי. tehorah legamrei. She's completely טהורה. tehorah. But if we
cannot attribute it to something external then she's טמאה. temeiah Now it's
purely rabbinic. But nevertheless there's ways in which we're stricter by כתם.
ketam. Because by a כתם, ketam, sorry, when she sees it from
her body then we say it probably came very recently. So we
can limit it to like twenty-four hours and similar types of things.
When it came from a כתם ketam with a stain on the
cloth, who knows? Maybe it was there for the last day, maybe
she's been a נידה niddah two days. a week, maybe she's been
a נדה for a longer period. So although it's Rabbinic, once we
make her טמאה, temeiah there could be more strict consequences. And this
is clear in the משנה Mishna because the משנה Mishna says the
חכמים agreed to רבי עקיבא that if she's טמאה temeiah, because of
a כתם, ketem, the husband is considered to be as טמא tamei
as his wife. They had sex during the period where now you
think that she might have been a נדה because of this stain
on the cloth. So in this case, because it's more seriously likely
that she was טמאה temeiah earlier because again, when she sees it
from her body, it's most likely it happened just in the last
few seconds. When you see it in the cloth, then if we're
going to assume she's טמאה, temeiah there is a more serious likelihood
that it really was a case a good while earlier. So we're
going to make the husband as טמא tamei as the wife if
they had sex during that period.
What's wet stains and dry stains?
Yeah, that's all going to come up later. There's a whole פרקים
prakim devoted to כתמים. ketamim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מודים
חכמים לרבי עקיבא בכתם. modim Chachamim le-Rabbi Akiva be-ketem. אמר רב למפרע.
amar Rav le-mafrei'a.
That means going back. Going back all the time we'll say that
she's טמאה temeiah because of the stain until the last time the
cloth was checked. Then if they had sex any time in that
previous time, he is טמא tamei as she is. רבי מאיר היא.
Rabbi Meir hi. And it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says this
הלכה halacha that when a woman who's טמאה temeiah, because of כתם
ketem all the way back, the husband if he had sex is
טמא tamei, as she is. ושמואל אמר מכאן ולהבא ורבנן היא. u-Shmuel
amar mikan u-le-haba ve-rabbanan hi. No,
it's the rabbis who argue on רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Again, we
saw this debate earlier, we'll see it again but we're not quoting
it here, that say that when a woman is טמאה temeiah retroactively
because of a כתם, ketem, her husband is not as טמא tamei
as she is even if they had sex.
So therefore, what does משנה Mishna mean when it says the rabbis
agree that the husband is as טמא tamei as she is? It
means if they have sex after she finds the stain, not in
the period from before she finds the stain. So the גמרא Gemara
says מכאן ולהבא? mikan u-le-haba? After she found the stain? From that
point onwards? פשיטא. pshita. Of course he's as טמא tamei as she
is. She's definitely טמאה, temeiah at least Rabbinically, and he's going to
have sex with her and so he's going to be as טמא
as she is. No. מהו דתימא? mahu de-teima? I might have thought.
הואיל ומעת לעת דרבנן. ho'il u-mei-eit le-eit de-rabbanan. Since the whole 24-hour
retroactive is a Rabbinic טומאה. וכתמים דרבנן. ve-ketamim de-rabbanan. And making a
woman טמאה tmeiah, because of a stain on the cloth is, I
don't know, on the bedsheet let's say, is Rabbinic. So the same
way we have leniencies in the last 24 hours. מה מעת לעת
לא מטמא את בועלה? mah mei-eit le-eit lo metamei et bo'alah?
The same way when we do the 24 hours backwards, we do
make a distinction, we say the husband is only the status of
a ראשון. He's not an אב. He's not as טמא as she
is if they had sex in the last 24 hours. So even
though it's definite Rabbinic טומאה, we do not give it its full
force. So maybe we would say the same by stains even going
forward. אף כתמים. af ketamim. So he's טמא for touching her because
she was a נדה, but he's not as טמא, he's not an
אב. So let's say the exact same as we say backwards of
the 24 hours, we'll say forwards of the כתמים. ketamim. אף כתמים
לא מטמא את בועלה? af ketamim lo metamei et bo'alah?
Maybe the same would be true of כתמים ketamim that he would
not be as טמא as she even going forward since the whole
thing is Rabbinic. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So it tells
you no, we're stricter by כתמים ketamim again. Well, by כתמים ketamim
going forward than we are by the 24 hours backwards. So now
the גמרא Gemara's said that was a really good point you just
made. ואימא הכי נמי? ve-eima hachi nami? Why not say that? כתמים
ketamim is Rabbinic, so if we have a certain leniency by the
24 hours backwards, let's also have a leniency by the stains going
forward since it's all Rabbinic. So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם
אין שור שחוט לפניך. hatam ein shor shachut lefanecha. About the last
24 hours, here's a colorful image that the גמרא Gemara has, which
says there's got to be a good English idiom for this, but
the גמרא's Gemara idiom is the ox is slaughtered in your presence,
which means if the evidence is already there's a problem.
Anyway, in the last 24 hours there's no knowledge to say that
there was a problem. Meaning you don't have the actual problem staring
you in the face. During those last 24 hours there was no
knowledge she was a נדה. We're only sort of retrojecting it backwards.
So therefore we're going to be more lenient, which underscores the idea
that we don't really know whether she was טמאה tmeiah or not,
and therefore we're going to have that leniency although we have a
Rabbinic טומאה. הכא, hacha, in this case, יש שור שחוט לפניך. yesh
shor shachut lefanecha. The stain is in front of you. So going
forward, it's true that we're not exactly sure did the stain come
from her or not or whatever, it is Rabbinic, but we've got
the problem staring us in the face. Maybe that would be the
good idiom. The problem is staring us in the face. If the
problem is staring us in the face, we're not going to make
distinctions. The reason we can make distinctions in the last 24 hours
was for that time during those last 24 hours the problem was
not staring us in the face. וכן אמר ריש לקיש דלמפרע ורבי
מאיר היא. ve-chen amar Resh Lakish de-le-mafrei'a ve-Rabbi Meir hi. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish says the rabbis when it says in the משנה Mishna
the rabbis agree by כתמים ketamim that the husband is as טמא
as she is, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that's strict by כתמים.
ketamim. ורבי יוחנן אמר, ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar, no, מכאן ולהבא. mikan u-le-haba.
Our משנה Mishnah is only going from this point forward. ורבנן היא,
ve-rabbanan hi, and it is the rabbis who are more lenient with
the previous
period by כתמים ketamim but going
forward. or not and now we get to a very important idea
which we had also discussed a few days ago. This is another
one of the very important locations about not about the טומאה וטהרה
tum'ah v'taharah world but about for us now and assumptions about we
discussed when do women have to check and we basically concluded that
for us now when it's not a world of טומאה וטהרה tum'ah
v'taharah women do not need to and should not check before and
after sex
and because that just will make it create greater anxiety and there's
no need when you're not dealing in a טומאה וטהרה tum'ah v'taharah
world and that theme is now repeated in this משנה Mishnah with
continued discussion. So let's take a look. Here's what the משנה Mishnah
says.
Wait isn't that just for אשה שיש לה וסת? isha she'yesh la
veset?
Well we said even for according to שמואל Shmuel even אשה שאין
לה וסת isha she'ein la veset does not have to check before
and after sex and that's the general consensus of the פסק. psak.
כל הנשים בחזקת טהרה לבעליהן. kol hanashim be'chezkat taharah le'ba'aleihen. All women
are when it comes to not טומאה וטהרה. tum'ah v'taharah. טומאה וטהרה
tum'ah v'taharah you're checking before and after sex but when it comes
to the question about having sex without the context of טומאה וטהרה
tum'ah v'taharah all women are considered טהורה. tehorah. Now that means that
if she knew beforehand she was not a נדה once she's known
a נדה then you have to change that חזקה chazakah but they
continue to have a status of טהורה tehorah and you're not concerned
there's not a concern that she just bled right now. She's not
concerned and he is not concerned unless you absolutely know otherwise. So
that's basically saying explaining why there's no need for checking when you're
not in a world of טומאה וטהרה tum'ah v'taharah because there's an
assumption everything remains okay. הבא מן הדרך ha-ba min haderech now here's
another example of this okay which is somebody was away and he
comes home after a trip. אשתו משולמת לו בחזקת טהרה. ishto meshulemet
lo be'chezkat taharah. He can assume his wife is טהורה tehorah now
that you would say didn't he just say that but actually that's
a big חידוש chiddush because how long have you been away on
your trip? Right if the guy's been away for more than a
month so why can he make an
assumption? Right if the guy was away for a week or day
or he comes home at night so the question is do I
have to ask my wife right oh did you become a נדה
today? Does she have to check? Do I have to ask her?
And the answer to all that is no. If she was טהורה
tehorah this morning or yesterday then the man can assume she's טהורה
tehorah this evening without her having to check without him having to
ask. But you can't
make that assertion if the guy's coming home after a month. So
we'll have to see about that in the גמרא Gemara but the
second line is not nearly as obvious as the first.
Do we assume this משנה Mishnah was composed later than the others?
You mean why would a משנה Mishnah deal with a non-right
but maybe not to like why לבעליהן le'ba'aleihen why doesn't it just
say בחזקת טהרה? be'chezkat taharah?
Because they're not בחזקת טהרה be'chezkat taharah in a world of טומאה
וטהרה. tum'ah v'taharah. They're checking five times a day whatever.
So was it a later משנה Mishnah then?
It was described well it might be describing remember we said עסוקה
בטהרות asuka be'taharot and לא עסוקה בטהרות lo asuka be'taharot so if
that does not mean a historical period if it means certain women
care about טהרות taharot and others don't.
כל הנשים לבעליהן kol hanashim le'ba'aleihen meaning when it comes to a
concern of husbands and not a larger concern of טהרות. taharot. But
you're right one gets a sense that it's I don't know it's
a good question. Was it coming at a time when nobody was
worried about טהרה taharah so this was the rule for everybody? Or
was it saying כל הנשים kol hanashim that are not when it's
only about the husband and it's not about טהרות? taharot? Because some
women if you're a type of woman that generally is being careful
about טהרות taharot you've got all these issues to be concerned about.
I
guess meaning you know
what I'm thinking about is the following maybe and I say this
very tentatively maybe you could even go as far as suggesting that
it means the following: Let's say you are עסוקה בטהרות asuka be'taharot
so I say as a woman עסוקה בטהרות asuka be'taharot you should
be checking before and after sex. But if you you should also
be checking twice a day. But if you didn't check before and
after sex okay is it let's say does that now mean it's
אסור assur to have sex or that just means you didn't satisfy
your טהרות taharot requirements? You know what I mean? So let's say
a woman generally is checking twice a day and before and after
sex
and the husband I don't know is pressuring her and whatever the
case is and wants to have sex and so she didn't check.
Is it מותר mutar for them to have sex or is it
is it מותר mutar for them to have sex but she's violating
her טהרות taharot sort of obligation or does not checking actually mean
in that context that they shouldn't be having sex? So it's possible
to read the משנה Mishnah that way that's an interesting point. You
know maybe the משנה Mishnah even women that are עסוקה בטהרות when
it comes to the question of am I allowed to have sex
with my husband if I did or didn't check the answer is
yes you're allowed. You might have a טהרה taharah requirement but that
doesn't become a barrier to the question of
היתר לבעלה. hetter le'ba'alah. Yeah but it's an interesting possibility about how
to read that because the משנה Mishna. is not talking about time
periods it's talking about for what purpose. For טהרה Taharah purpose you
should be checking. But for having sex you don't have to be
checking. Right, so that's a very good read of that משנה. Mishna
Yes, I have to see if others confirm that, but it's a
very possible read. Saul, you want to say something? No, let's make,
let's move a little. So the Gemara says like this: למה לי
למיתני הבא מן הדרך? Lama li lemisni haba min haderech? Why does
it have to give that case? So I already told you why
it has to be the case. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina,
I would have thought הני מילי היכא דאיתיה במתא. Hanei milei heicha
de'isaya bemasa. So the Gemara actually gives a different reason than I
did. I talked about lengths of time which will come up in
a minute in the Gemara. But here's the reason the Gemara gives:
maybe if the husband was in the city, he's gone away for
a day or two or whatever, then I could say רמיא אנפשה
ובדקה. Ramya anafshah ubadkah. Then I could say that maybe she knows
her husband's coming home tonight or you know, and therefore she'll be
checking. And so the reason she's בחזקת טהרה Bechezkas tahara doesn't really
mean she doesn't have to check. It means she, we assume she
checked and she would have said otherwise to her husband. So again
it's talking to the men, not to the women, saying you guy,
you don't have to be concerned your wife is a נדה because
she would have checked and she would have told you if she
was. What, yeah, and she would have told you otherwise. Maybe I
would have read the משנה Mishna that way. אבל היכא דליתיה במתא,
Aval heicha deleisay bemasa, meaning not what we said. I would have
read the משנה Mishna the reason the man can assume she's טהורה
Tehorah is because he can assume she would have told me otherwise.
אבל היכא דליתיה במתא, Aval heicha deleisay bemasa, but when he wasn't
in the city and he comes home, you know, after being away
for a long time, and you know, they didn't have like flight
arrivals so they didn't know when the husband was coming home. דלא
רמיא אנפשה Delo ramya anafshah and she's not expecting him, she's not
bothering to check. Why? He's away for a month. So לא, I
would think that the man can't assume she's טהורה Tehorah because I
can't say oh, she would have told me otherwise. Maybe she hasn't
been checking. Maybe, maybe I, and maybe, so that's why she's not
telling me she's a נדה, not because she checked and it's okay,
maybe it's because she didn't check. So maybe I should, we should
wait till she checks before having sex. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that
that's not the reason. Meaning the important point here is not קמשמע
לן Kamashma lan that the woman checks even when the husband isn't
at home. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that the reason she's טהורה Tehorah
is not because I assume she checked and she would have said
something. The reason she's טהורה Tehorah is because there's no need to
be checking. So that's a major point. Don't read the משנה that
the man can assume she's טהורה Tehorah because he can assume she
would have told me otherwise. It's not that, it's not that. That
she's טהורה Tehorah also means that she can assume she's טהורה, Tehorah,
there's no need to check. Yes, Michael. Yeah, let's, let's hold off
the questions. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיאה. Amar Reish
Lakish mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesia. Reish Lakish said in the name of
Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, not Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi's grandson. והוא
שבא ומצאה בתוך ימי עונתה. Vehua sheba umatz'ah besoch yemei onasah. Now,
now we get to time. When can he assume when he comes
back is when he came back and it's still within a month
from her last period, or whatever her her cycle is. So he's
returning before her cycle is expected again. Okay, that's when he can
assume she's still טהורה. Tehorah. כגון שיש לה וסת Kegon sheyesh lah
veset or we might assume a regular thirty days without a וסת,
Veset, then he can assume.
אמר רב הונא לא שנו אלא שאין לה וסת. Amar Rav Huna
lo shanu ela she'ein lah veset. This idea that the husband can
assume that she's טהורה Tehorah is only when she does not have
a וסת. Veset. אבל יש לה וסת, Aval yesh lah veset, if
she has a regular cycle, אסור. Assur. She's forbidden. Now that sounds
bizarre, אסור לשמש. Assur lishamesh. The Gemara says: איפכא ליה? Ipcha leih?
Like, what does, it's a phrase which means like, what are you
talking about?
The opposite makes sense. אדרבה, Adarabba, the opposite, איפכא מסתברא, Ipcha mistabra,
the opposite makes sense. אין לה וסת, Ein lah veset, if she
has no fixed period, אימא חזאי, Eima chazai, maybe she saw at
any particular time. יש לה וסת, Yesh lah veset, if she has
a fixed period, וסתה קביע לה, Vestah kavia lah, then it's established
and if it's prior to that period, then he can assume that
she's still
טהורה. Tehorah. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר, Ela ei ismar hachi ismar,
here's how you have to say it. אמר רב הונא לא שנו
אלא שלא הגיע שעת וסתה. Amar Rav Huna lo shanu ela shelo
higia shas vestah. When can he, which is basically a reframing of
what we said a second ago. When can, if he comes back
after a long trip, assume that she's טהורה? Tehorah? If her expected
time of having her period has not yet arrived. אבל הגיע שעת
וסתה, Aval higia shas vestah, if he returns after the time of
expecting her period has arrived, אסורה, Asura, then she is forbidden. Now
by the way, Tosafot says this really doesn't contradict the point before,
because if a woman doesn't have a וסת, Veset, then there's no
time of period that he has to be concerned about. So in
an ironic way she's more טהורה. Tehorah. If a woman has a
regular period, then he has to assume after day thirty, if he
returns after day thirty, she probably had her period, she's אסורה. Asura.
If she doesn't have a fixed time, then maybe she forever? Now
that's the thing though. By the way, a woman who doesn't have
a fixed time, we don't say she's never going to get a
period. So we sort of create a
thirty-day sort of pseudo-period to assume that most women will see by
thirty days and that serves even for a woman without a fixed
period as a, you know, as a terminal point. Okay, but there
is certainly, but the point, but but the point is is that
with a period, then there's significance to passing a line of the
period or not. Okay. קסבר וסתות דאורייתא. Kasavar vesasos d'Oraisa.
Now this is going to be the big discussion for the rest
of today and tomorrow, which is a woman who has a regular
period, do we assume that her need to expect that she's going
to see on that day is a biblical need or a rabbinic?
Now why shouldn't it be biblical? If she... Establishes a regular pattern,
it's a חזקה Chazakah. *chazaka*, that should be regular. So maybe because
these things change, חזקה דעשויה להשתנות *chazaka d'asuiya l'ishtanos*, women's periods don't
always remain fixed and so on. But there's another idea, which is
there are really two important principles about what it means about a
וסת veses *vesset* and I'll discuss this more later but I need
to say it up front. It's developed by one of the ראשונים
*rishonim* mostly by the אחרונים *achronim*. And the idea is, it's one
thing to say I'm expecting to get my period today and we
have to deal with the possibility I might get my period, and
therefore the couple shouldn't be having sex. And that's one of the
הלכות *halachos* about during the time a woman is expecting her period
they're not allowed to have sex because she could become a נדה
*niddah* at any minute. That's one of the things. That's presumably could
be argued is דאורייתא *d'oraisa* according to everybody. Okay, or certainly is
more of a reason to say that you should be concerned about
that. Then there's another
question. The day 30 passed, day of the period passed, and you
didn't check. So before day 30, she had a חזקת טהרה *chazakas
tahara*. Now it's day 31. Does the expecting of the period enough
to change her prior status quo? And that might not be even
if there's an expectation of the period and that expectation is biblical
and you have to act appropriately, it might not be strong enough
and definite enough to change the status quo. So here וסתות דאורייתא
*vestos d'oraisa* means we could treat it as so biblical and so
weighty that we assume that her status quo is definitely changed. So
here he is saying, now again, why do you have to say
that? Maybe it just means that there's enough of a doubt that
they shouldn't be having sex? But anyway, the language of אסורה *asura*
sounds like definitely אסורה *asura*, not just you have to check. So
that is קסבר וסתות דאורייתא *ksavar vestos d'oraisa*. Once the time passes,
she has to assume unless she knows definitely otherwise that she is
a נדה *niddah* and that is because of וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'oraisa*,
the expectation tells us that she has definitely seen unless we have
evidence
otherwise. Does this come after
she had it on or after the day of the period? Usually
comes two months later? Well, we'll get to that. רבה בר בר
חנה אמר *Rabba bar bar Chana amar* אפילו הגיע שעת וסתה higia
shas vesta. נמי מותרת *afilu higia sha'as vestah nami muteres*. No, even
if she comes back on day 31, or maybe day 50, or
who knows? I mean, but day 31 is the bigger חידוש *chiddush*.
She remains מותרת *muteres*. Why? קסבר וסתות דרבנן DeRabbanan. *ksavar vestos d'rabanan*.
וסתות *vestos* are rabbinic and it does not change her status quo.
So he means this in the absolute. The husband left his wife,
she was טהורה tehorah. *tehora*.
He comes back a month later
or 30 days later or the day or the week after his
period. He can assume maybe she's still טהורה tehorah. *tehora*. That was
her status before. The fact that she probably got that she might
have gotten her period is a
ספק Safeik. *safek*. She didn't definitely
get her period. It doesn't override her previous status quo. Of course,
the
question is as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
frames elsewhere וכי לעולם לא תראה *vechi l'olam lo
tireh*? What, I guess she's never going to bleed? Well, but by
the way, they didn't have birth control in those days. So women
weren't נדה *niddah* so often. Women were pregnant a lot. So that's
also something to
think about, how definite it is. But anyway, there is a question
how far would you take that? But he basically says it does
not change the
status quo. רב אשי מתני הכי *Rav Ashi masni hachi*. Take it
a
step further? He just had something to ask. Presumably, he doesn't even
need to ask her. Now, there's a little debate about רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* throws in, which is not
in the
גמרא *Gemara*, and if she were a נדה *niddah* she would have
told him. Because רש"י *Rashi* seems to be a little concerned like
this question like, okay, maybe you don't say it
definitely happened, but shouldn't you have to
check? I mean, isn't there, would you forever say it didn't happen?
So רש"י *Rashi* throws in the idea oh and she would have
told him if there was some... alright alright, let's go on. רב
אשי מתני הכי *Rav Ashi masni hachi*. also contributes to our assumptions.
All right, that would be different.
Right. Unclear because it's still her will, free will. רבה בר בר
חנה אמר אפילו יש לה וסת לימים מותרת, afilu yesh la veses
l'yomim mutesres, and here's the other opinion, even if it's a regular
natural cycle of days and he comes back after that period, she
is permissible, not even a ספק, safeik again, quite fascinating. קסבר וסת
דרבנן, kasavar veses d'rabbanan, that is rabbinic. אמר רב שמואל משמיה דרבי
יוחנן, Amar Rav Shmuel mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan, so Shmuel said in the
name of Rabbi Yochanan, אשה שיש לה וסת, ishah she'yesh la veses,
remember same Shmuel who said that even a woman without a וסת
doesn't have to check for her husband? But again, that was prior,
that was not הגיע שעת וסתה. Now we are dealing with a
different question we did not deal with before, which is the time
of her period has arrived. Okay, so that's very different than the
previous question, which was just in the middle of the month her
having sex. אשה שיש לה וסת, ishah she'yesh la veses, if a
woman has a fixed period, בעלה מחשב ימי וסתה ובעלה. ba'ala mechashiv
yemei vesta u'ba'ala.
So the husband presumably means the husband is away, and again, the
kids can say, okay, let's see. I've been away now for three
weeks, she was expecting her period, you know, ten days ago, so
that was long enough for her to have gotten her period, have
waited seven days and gone to the מקווה. mikvah. So I can
assume that she is טהורה. tehorah. So it's the flip side of
saying after the day passes, right, he has to assume she's טמאה,
tmeiah but he can also with certainty assume that she
started on that day, that it was over seven days later, because
remember this is time when you don't need clean days, so it'll
definitely be over seven days later, and that she went to the
מקווה. mikvah. And if that has passed, the period plus seven days,
then he can assume that she is טהורה. Now of course an
ongoing question here which we raised before is what's all this "he
assumes, he assumes, he assumes"? Like, why isn't he asking her? Right?
And that again gets to the question about how much, you know,
is she half awake or those types of issues, but you know,
it raises those troubling issues we raised before, but it bears mentioning.
You know, what does this mean ובעלה? u'ba'ala? He comes home and
he has sex with her? Why wouldn't he say so ask her,
"did you go to the מקווה?" mikvah? So, "all right, I didn't
want to wake her up, I didn't want to bother her." I
mean, so but that's a problem, that's making some of those assumptions.
But if he came within, let's say four days after? Yes, and
then no, right, right.
Okay. אמר ליה רב שמואל בר ייבא לרב אבא, amar lei Rav
Shmuel bar Yeva l'Rav Abba, אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו ילדה דבזיזא למיטבל?
amar Rabbi Yochanan afilu yaldah d'beziza l'mitvhal? Would Rabbi Yochanan say this?
Because this was in the name of Rabbi Yochanan. Now there's two
ways of reading this. רש"י reads this, would he say this even
about a child? Again, because we have those scenarios we talked about
before, but the גמרא is not bothered with, about married to under-age
girls. So even a child that she's embarrassed to go to the
מקווה, mikvah, you know, young girl going to the מקווה, mikvah, whatever,
so she would only do it if her husband was pressuring her,
not if her husband is away. So maybe he- you can't assume
that she's gone to the מקווה. mikvah. That's the way רש"י reads
it. תוספות Tosafos. reads it not ילדה yaldah like a small child,
but more like יולדת. yoledes. Even a woman that has just given
childbirth recently and she is not embarrassed, but she is afraid. Like
she doesn't want to submerge herself in water, like for her health
issues. Okay, so דבזיזא d'beziza he says does not mean embarrassed, but
means afraid to go to the מקווה. mikvah. Take a look at
תוספות. Tosafos, Anyway,
so what would you say it even when there's a concern that
she would not have gone to the מקווה? mikvah? So אמר ליה
אטו ודאי ראתה מי אמר רבי יוחנן? amar lei atu vadai rassa
mi amar Rabbi Yochanan? Rabbi Yochanan is not talking that we know
she definitely went to the mik- even if she definitely is טמאה
we can say she definitely went to the מקווה. mikvah. אימא דאמר
רבי יוחנן, eima d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, what's Rabbi Yochanan talking about? ספק
ראתה ספק לא ראתה. safek rassa safek lo rassa. He is not
saying וסת דאורייתא, veses d'oraisa, as we assumed a minute ago. He
is saying I don't know if she had her period. So because
I don't know if she had her period, וסת דרבנן, veses d'rabbanan,
I don't know for sure she went to the מקווה, mikvah, but
I can add, maybe she had her period, maybe she didn't, but
even if she did, maybe she went to the מקווה. mikvah. So
those things allow the husband to assume that she is טהורה. It
is the combination of the two. Okay, ספק ראתה ספק לא ראתה
ואם תמצא לומר ראתה אימת טבלה? safek rassa safek lo rassa v'im
timtzo lomar rassa eimat tavla? Even if she had her period, maybe
she went to the מקווה. mikvah. אבל ודאי ראתה, aval vadai rassa,
and this way it works better for תוספות, Tosafot in a case
where she definitely saw, let's say childbirth, where she starts being טמאה
and then there's a doubt if she went to the מקווה, mikvah,
מי אמר דטבלה? mi amar d'tavla? I cannot say she definitely went
to the מקווה. mikvah. הוי ליה ספק וודאי ואין ספק מוציא מידי
ודאי. havei lei safek v'vadai v'ein safek motzi midei vadai. Then there's
a definite טומאה, definite נידה, niddah, a questionable fix, a questionable did
she go to the מקווה mikvah or not? And that cannot change
the status quo. And this is now going and we have a
few minutes to begin this next discussion. So a shift from a
סוגיא sugya about וסת דאורייתא, veses d'oraisa, for the rest of this
דף daf we'll get back to וסת דאורייתא, veses d'oraisa, is going
to be the question about ספק מוציא מידי ודאי, safek motzi midei
vadai, which is the following: somebody has a definite status of being
טמא or אסור assur or food has or whatever, but you have
the ability to change it. Okay, it's in your power to change
it. But I don't know if you did it or not. Can
I rely on the assumption that oh of course you will change,
you will make it good? Or not, maybe you know at the
end of the day I- that's not 100 percent and I can't
assume you did what would have been required to have been done.
So that is the idea. If we would have said וסת דאורייתא.
veses d'oraisa. If we would have said זה דאורייתא zeh Deoraita and
the woman was definitely in נדה, then I couldn't, then the husband
couldn't assume that she definitely went to the מקווה, Mikvah, because you
can't assume אין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. Ein Safeik Motzi Midei Vadai.
Even though it would have made sense and it would normally have
happened, can't assume that. Okay, but why did רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
say it? Because she was only questionably a נדה, that's דרבנן. And
therefore he can assume that's enough to assume she went to the
מקווה. Mikvah. So now the גמרא is going to shift to look
at that question. When something is definite problematic, can you now assume
that something happened to fix it without definitely knowing otherwise? So let's,
so that's why תוספות read of יהודית' Yehudis words better. Let's read
at least the beginning of that discussion. ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי?
Ve'ein Safeik Motzi Midei Vadai? Is it really true that a ספק
cannot change a ודאי? Vadai? Now again, if it was a real
ספק, 50-50, of course it can't change a ודאי. Vadai. That's the
whole הלכה Halakha of status quo and חזקה. But here, as I
framed it to you, it's not any ספק. It's a highly likely
thing and you could have done it and I just wanted to
know, did you do what you should have been doing? Okay, or
whatever it is, it's a highly likely. So highly likely enough to
change the status quo. So the גמרא says, let's read one example.
דהא תניא: חבר שמת והניח מגורה מלאה פירות. Deha Tanya: Chaveir she'meis
vehinniah megurah malei peiros. Somebody who's a חבר, Chaveir, somebody who's very
scrupulous about תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot u'Ma'asrot, he dies and his, you know,
threshing floor was filled with grain. Now, did he take תרומות ומעשרות
Terumot u'Ma'asrot or not? אפילו הן בני יומן, Afillu hein b'nei yoman,
even if they were, it was just threshed today, הרי הן בחזקת
מתוקנים. Harei hein b'chezkat metukkanim. You can assume he took care of
it. So why can you? Because he's a good guy, he would
have taken care of it on the same day. Okay, but it's
not 100%. והכא
בודאי טבל, ספק מעושר ספק אינו מעושר. Vehakha b'vadai tevel, safeik meusar
safeik ein meusar. It started off definitely problematic, definitely טבל. tevel. There's
a question whether he took it or not. And even though we
know he's a good guy and almost definitely, it's still almost definitely,
it's not definite. וקאתי ספק ומוציא מידי ודאי. Veka'asi safeik umotzi midei
vadai. And that changes the status quo, that almost definitely. So the
גמרא says, התם ודאי ודאי הוא. Hatam vadai vevadai hu. No, it's
a ודאי. vadai. Why is it a
ודאי? vadai? דאמר רבי חנינא חוזה, De'amar Rabbi Chanina Chuzah, דאמר רבי
חנינא חוזה: de'amar Rabbi Chanina Chuzah: חזקה על חבר שאינה מוציא מתחת
ידו דבר שאינו מתוקן. Chazakah al chaveir she'eina motzi mitachat yado davar
she'eino metukkan. That it is a ודאי, vadai, that it's not an
almost ודאי. vadai. Sometimes we actually say it's definite. We can trust
a חבר chaveir that he won't let the day go without actually
taking care of it. So sometimes almost definite becomes definite based on
assumptions of human nature and we turn it into a ודאי. vadai.
And we'll just see the last answer. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, I
don't care, ספק בספק הוא. safeik besafeik hu. It wasn't definitely problematic
like the woman who didn't definitely have her
period. כדרבי אושעיא, Kide'Rabbi Oshia, דאמר רבי אושעיא: de'amar Rabbi Oshia: מערים
אדם על תבואתו ומכניסה במוצלה, Maarim adam al tevuato u'machnisah b'motzlo, a
person can trick, can scheme, and he can bring the grain into
the threshing floor, wherever it was, with its chaff. כדי שתהא בהמה
אוכלת ופטורה מן המעשר. Kedei shetehei behemah ochelet u'peturah min hama'aser. That
he can feed to his animal and it could be exempt. Why?
Biblically you're only obligated in מעשר Ma'aser if you first winnow it
in the field and then after winnowing bring it in. But if
you bring it in with the chaff and the finishing process is
after it's been brought into the house, it's not biblically obligated. So
therefore we don't know that happened here, but we don't know it's
definite טבל דאורייתא, tevel Deoraita, because there's a possibility otherwise. So that's
enough to say, okay, 95% it was, but there's a 5% not.
But there's also 95% that he fixed it. So that's enough to
change something that is not a ודאי. vadai. So we will continue
tomorrow with this question about something that has a definite status quo
and a high likelihood and almost definite it is fixed. Is almost
definite enough to change? But there's two ways of saying it works.
One is that the original status quo wasn't 100%, it was 95%.
And the other way of saying it works is that the idea
that it was definitely fixed, we're going to consider it as if
that was 100%. Okay, but what we want to figure out is,
what's the story when we consider the original status 100% and the
possibility of being fixed
95%? Will ספק be מוציא מידי ודאי? motzi midei vadai? Until tomorrow.